Employed Wangfu Dean and our
就業的王府院長以及我們
Please, vice presidents, ladies up front.
請各位副總裁 前面的女士
and our Dean Wu
以及我們吳院長
Dear colleagues, fellow students
各位同仁 各位同學
Good morning everybody
大家早安
Good morning
早安
Today is after I take office
今天是我上任以後
Organized academic lectures for the first time
第一次組織學術員講
Very happy to organize this
非常高興就來組織這個
about us
有關我們前事領
An academic lecture by the former principal
前校長的一個學術講座
The former headmaster is something we admire very much.
那前校長是我們非常敬佩的
a principal
一個校長
Because he was in the 40th to 59th years of the Republic of China
因為他在民國40年到59年
Served as principal for 19 years
擔任了19年的校長
The fifth principal of Zhiwen School
志文本校的第五任的校長
He is overall in the administration of our school
他整體在我們學校的行政上面
done a lot of work
做了非常多的工作
Especially the administrative system of our whole school
尤其是我們整個學校的行政體系
and recruitment
還有招募人才
On the other hand
另外一方面的話
Thematic planning and cooperation with outside property rights
專題企劃跟外面的產權合作
established a very complete system
建立了非常完整的體系
Even the work of the China Merchants Association
甚至連招聯會的工作
He built it
都是他建立起來的
Therefore, the 19-year principal has contributed a lot to the school
所以19年的校長對學校貢獻非常巨大
I am careful, everyone has seen it in my newspaper
我仔細 各位都看到我報紙上
People say I've been doing administrative work for a long time
人家說我做了很久的行政工作
From the director to the dean to the current principal
從所長一直當到院長到現在校長
In fact, I haven't been doing it for 19 years
事實上我也還沒做滿19年
I did it for 17.5 years
我一共做了17.5年
So your ex-principal also played music
所以你以前校長還音樂
Especially after I was elected as the principal
尤其我當選這個校長之後
Start to keep in mind the school rules
開始去對學校的事情 記緊規
Only then did I know that being the principal
才曉得說做校長
The president of National Taiwan University is also very lenient
台大校長管得也很寬
So we can appreciate that the former headmaster
所以我們就可以體會到前校長
It's not easy, of course, the 19-year-old president of National Taiwan University
是多麼不容易的當然19年的台大校長
Because NTU itself is a representative of Taiwan
因為台大本身是台灣的一個代表
So not just administrative work in schools
所以不只是在學校的行政工作
in the overall political system
在整體的政治體制
Response to government Response to international
因應政府 因應國際
due to our old loss
因應我們的老失去
It's a very, very difficult job
這是一個非常非常不容易的工作
so i'm really happy today
所以我今天真的非常的高興
I will host
我來主持
We invite the principal to give a lecture
我們請校長的一個講座
Then we will do it with you today
那我們今天來跟各位來做
It is our Zheng Yue'e who gave the speech
演講的是我們鄭月娥
Our Academician Zheng
我們鄭院士
He is also our chair professor at National Taiwan University.
也是我們台大的講座教授
I am very interested in the topic he talked about
他講的題目我很有興趣
Because he talked about the evolution of Chinese characters
因為他講的是有關於漢字的演變
Academician Zheng Academician Zheng I'm sorry
鄭院士 鄭院士 對不起
sorry so he himself
抱歉 所以他本身
I think Academician Zheng's voice is
我想鄭院士的聲就
I don't need to talk
我就不用多講
everyone knows everyone
大家都對大家都很熟
he is mainly in this
他主要是在這個
Combining Five Points of Literature
結合五點文學
Western literature
跟現在西方文學
I think he's a very good example of a domain
我想他是一個非常劃領域的典範
In particular, he put the western space
尤其他把西方空間
or body
或身體
Combined with Five Points Literature
跟五點文學做了結合
What he said today has something to do with this
今天他講的也是跟這個有點關係
Just look at the evolution of our Chinese characters
就是看我們漢字的演變
I think today's speech is also very exciting
我想今天的演講也非常的精彩
really happy today
今天真的非常高興
especially when we passed a year
尤其我們過了一年
It was very cold during the Chinese New Year ahead
本來前面在過年期間都非常冷
Today looks sunny
今天看起來陽光古造
I'm sure I heard a very wonderful story today
我相信今天有聽到一個非常精彩的
once again i thank you all for your attendance
我再次謝謝大家的出席
I also wish you all a healthy, safe and happy new year
也祝福大家新的一年健康平安快樂
thank you all
謝謝大家
This is what our central government posted about configuration considerations.
這個我們中央就很貼出配置思考
In fact I don't need to rely on this thinking
事實上我不需要依賴這個思考
I'm for this
我對這個來說
to former dean
對前院長
Our former dean is very respectful
我們前院長非常的尊敬
all admire him
都相當的佩服他
In fact former principal
事實上前校長
former principal
前校長
our dean
我們的院長
Both have served very long in both academic institutions
都是在兩個學術機構服務非常的長久
13 years in Central
在中央就有13年
Is by far the longest serving dean
是到現在為止服務最久的一位院長
So he has a lot of buildings
所以他的建築非常的多
during his tenure
在他的任內
Five research institutes were established
成立了五個研究所
information center
資訊所
I don't care
我就不依依點
To prepare another five
要籌備另外五個所
Places like this human center
像這個人設中心這些所
So for the center to lay the next one
所以替中央就打下一個
very solid foundation
非常堅實的基礎
That's why we continue to carry forward his contribution today
所以我們今天才有繼續發揚他的貢獻
Central physicians should have the scale of today
中央醫師要有今天的規模
I don’t want to talk about being in National Taiwan University
對於在台大就不願意不用講
He has countless talents
他作意英才無數
Therefore, many teachers and students of National Taiwan University are very grateful to him.
所以很多台大老師跟學生到現都非常的感念他
Lecture by the Dean of the Former Faculty Principal
這個前師量校長院長的講座
As for the Central Research Institute and National Taiwan University
就中央研究員跟台大一起辦
Today we specially invited
今天我們特別請了
Special Professor of the Chinese Department of National Taiwan University
台大中文系的特別教授
Academician of Justice
正義院士
He is also an amalgamated professor at our Central Research Institute of Philosophy
他同時是我們中央研究文哲所的合併教授
His achievements in comparative literature
他的在比較文學的成就
It is obvious to all in the International College
在國際學院是有目共睹
I'm also very close to him personally.
我個人也對他非常的親配
I think we'll just leave the rest of the day to the Justice Fellows
我想我們就把剩下的時間留給正義院士
come sing his academic
來唱他的學術
I wish my heartfelt love and share it with everyone
祝了心疼 跟大家分享
Thank you all, happy new year and good work
謝謝大家 新年快樂 辦事如意
President Chen Vice President Huang of Central Hospital
陳校長 中央醫院的黃副院長
Today's keynote speaker, Academician Zheng
今天的主講人 鄭院士
Dear teachers, students, distinguished guests
各位老師 各位同學 各位貴賓
Good morning everybody
大家早安
good
好
It's a great honor to be here today
今天很榮幸的能在此地參加
Academic lectures in memory of the late father
為紀念先父的學術講座
This year is the 43rd and 39th
今年是第四十 三十九屆
Thirty-ninth time
第三十九次
For forty years since my father passed away
因為先父去世了四十年
I think today's lecture has two characteristics
我覺得今天的講座有兩個特點
The first feature we at National Taiwan University are very happy about
第一個特點我們臺大很高興的
And we have a very good new principal
又有了一位非常卓越的新校長
President Chen Wenwen
陳文章校長
We would like to take this opportunity to express to him
我們願意藉這個機會向他表示
Gong Hyuk means
是功赫的意思
I also hope that National Taiwan University will be under his leadership
也希望台大在他领导之下
To be able to come here to go one step further
能够来此干头更进一步
The second is today's chief general
第二就是今天的主将子
Academician Zheng
这个郑院士
The topic he spoke was very definite
他讲的题目非常的确定
Just now the headmaster said no
刚才校长已经提过不啰啰说了
But as far as my personal memory
不过就我个人的记忆
Because the last 34 years
因为最近这个34年
america back
美国回来
every year i attend
每一年我都参加
past 11 years
过去的11年
Every lecture is a natural science
每一个讲座都是自然科学
and biological sciences
和生物科学
It's hard today
今天好不容易
Come to a Humanities and Social Sciences Come to
来到一个人文社会科学来
And to find such a wonderful speaker
而且找到这么精彩的一位讲者
So I think today's lecture
所以我觉得今天的讲座
we can expect
我们是可以期待的
Today is the eleventh day of the first lunar month
今天是正月十一
remember
回忆
the eleventh day of the first lunar month of a certain year
某年的正月十一
haven't burnt yet
還沒有過燃燒
So I still have the opportunity to say goodbye to everyone here
所以還有機會在這裡向各位拜個晚年
I wish you all good luck in the new year
祝福各位新年 行大運
happy family, good health, good luck
家庭幸福美滿 身體健康 事實如意
Thanks
謝謝
former dean
前院長
Then Dean Huang Hu
然後黃沪院長
And our patriarch, Principal Chen
還有我們的大家長 陳校長
Good morning, my friends
還有好朋友們大家早安
really honored today
今天真的非常榮幸
Can serve as Mr. Si Liang, the former principal of Gu
可以擔任前顧校長思亮先生
115th Memorial Academic Lecture
一百一十五歲的紀念學術講座
In fact, in 2007, I personally
其實我個人在二零零七年
Also met the former dean at Yale University
在耶魯大學也遇見過前院長
I really admire his demeanor and eloquence.
對他的風範 口才真的是非常仰慕
So today we can actually meet
所以今天可以實際的來見面
I'm glad too
我也很高興
About the topic I want to talk to you today
那關於今天要跟各位講的題目
Actually the main
其實主要
I want to share a bit of my own research experience
想要分享一點我自己的一個研究的心得
it was at the beginning of the twentieth century
就是在二十世紀初
Some Thoughts on the Transformation of Chinese Characters or Chinese
漢字或漢語轉型的一些思考
So in particular, I will focus on the issue of heterosexuality
那麼尤其我會聚焦在多異性這個問題
What about this question?
那為了這個問題呢
I think we'll go back to language
我想我們就回到語言文字
The underlying assumption that is often referred to
很多時候會被提到的根本的假設
For example, if pragmatism prevails in the
比方說如果實用主義盛行底下
We will ask what is the use of language
我們就會問語言文字有什麼用
When you ask what is the use of language
當你問語言文字有什麼用的時候
Two basic assumptions emerge
會有兩個基本的設想出現
The first is that language is a tool
第一個就是語言文字就是一種工具
When you use language as a tool
當你把語言文字當成工具的時候
we imagine
我們想像
That could be, say, a truck carrying goods
那可能是比方說貨車載運貨物
So as long as he can carry
所以只要他能載送
any car will do
什麼車都可以
It seems that each session itself is not so important
好像每一屆本身並不是那麼重要
because he is just a tool
因為他只是一個工具
the second will involve
那第二個就會牽涉
The second imagination is language
第二個想像就是語言文字
probably just neutral transparent
可能只是中性透明的
like looking through a glass window
就好像透過玻璃窗
Because don't we see through it at a glance?
因為我們不是一眼就看穿了嗎
So in fact, this pregnant or existing
所以其實這個在孕的或者存在的
or the idea of ​​neutral transparency
或者是中性透明的想法
In fact, it affects our daily life
其實會影響我們在日常生活中
a lot of thinking and judgment
很多思考跟判斷
therefore
因此
If you think that the original text is just a tool for communication
如果你以為原文字只是溝通的工具
is neutral and transparent
是中性透明的
but you in your daily life
但是你在日常生活中
obviously often heard
明明常常聽到
why don't you understand my feelings
為什麼你不懂我的感受
so why don't you understand
所以為什麼不懂
these things are not
這些事情並不是
Just treat the original text as a tool
只是把原文字當成工具
it can be solved
就可以解決的
So I thought I'd take that angle today
所以我想我今天會從這個角度
the one everyone knows
大家都知道的一個
Thoughts about the original text
關於原文字的色想
to go
來出發
Then in the early twentieth century
然後以二十世紀初期的
Chinese characters
漢字漢語
Transformation especially in China
尤其在中國境內的轉型
make an example to illustrate
做一個例子來說明
for example
比方說
Everyone knows the second two yellow butterflies
大家都知道第二首兩個黃蝴蝶
written by Hu Shi
是胡適所寫的
Also considered the first heart poem in the vernacular
也被認為是白話的第一首心詩
what do you know about butterflies
你會知道蝴蝶呢
In these two contexts of classical and modern
在這前後兩個古典跟現代的語境裡面
it's not just a butterfly at all
它根本不只是蝴蝶
For example, the first one is familiar to everyone
比方說第一個大家都比較熟悉的
Learner Zhuangzhou dreams of being a butterfly
習者莊州夢為蝴蝶
It is the story of Zhuangzhou Dream Butterfly
就是莊州夢蝶的故事
look at the end
你看最後說
I don't know everyone knows that Meng is a butterfly fish
不知周知夢為蝴蝶魚
Butterfly is a dream for Zhou Yu
蝴蝶是夢為周魚
You know this punctuation mark is a posterity
你知道這個標點符號是後人家的
It turned out there wasn't
原來是沒有的
How does it break the sentence?
那它怎麼斷句呢
it uses virtual characters
它是用虛字的
For example, wild, fish, fish, etc.
比方說野啊 魚啊 魚啊等等這些
it uses these to make sentences
它是用這些來斷句
so you can find butterflies here
所以你可以發現在這裡蝴蝶
Of course not just butterflies
當然不只是蝴蝶啊
because it actually says
因為它其實是在講
between people and things
人跟物之間
I can communicate with each other
物我可以相互感通
But in this butterfly poem by Hu Shi
但是在胡適的這一首蝴蝶詩裡面
It obviously really wants to talk about why the two butterflies
它明顯就真的要講兩支蝴蝶為什麼
Because the poem was written when it was in New York
因為這首詩是寫於它在紐約
It's different from when I was studying in college
跟不一樣大學念書的時候
the apartment facing it
那面對它的公寓
Facing the Hudson River
面對著Hudson River
it sees two butterflies
它就看到兩支蝴蝶
fly around
飛來飛去
Are these two butterflies
那這兩支蝴蝶是有
number of two
有數量的兩個
and causally
而且有因果的
because how so how
因為怎麼樣所以怎麼樣
This perfectly echoes
這個完全呼應了
Hu Shi himself is very particular about
胡適自己非常講究的
In fact, language expression
其實語言表達
can only be precise
只能精確
and must be precise
而且一定要精確
Therefore, there must be a specified symbol
所以要有規定的符號
have grammar
要有文法
to be obvious
要明顯意見
and meaning
而且意義
to be sure
要確定不意
Here we can find
在這裡我們可以發現
Actually the word butterfly
其實單單蝴蝶這個字詞
in different uses
在不同的使用身上
polymorphism
它就形成了多異性
Originally heterosexual
本來多異性
In traditional Chinese characters
在傳統的漢語漢字裡面
no problem
沒有問題
but from now on
可是從現在開始
there is a problem
有了問題
Why
為什麼
Let's look at a lot of the background of the year
我們看看當年的很多背景
in 1933
在1933年
I found a popular science unique
我找到一個科普獨物
Science Pictorial
叫科學畫報
science pictorial is
科學畫報是
Science founded by the Chinese
中國人創辦的Science
Confederate Sole
底下的同盟獨物
Inside the science pictorial
那科學畫報裡面
One of them is called
其中有一篇叫
where for example
在那裡比方說
treat the human body as a machine
把人體看作機械
The brain is the general management office
而腦是總管理室
The mouth is the mouth is the entrance for the fuel
口就是嘴巴是燃料的入口
And the nose is like the fragrance blowing
而鼻子像是風香鼓動
In this mechanical view
在這個機械式的看法裡面
It has something to do with the entire machine civilization.
跟整個機器文明都有關係
Also 1930s
同樣也是 1930 年代
Louis Monford
Louis Monford
Inside Technics and Civilization
Technics and Civilization 裡面
The most famous is the classification of space-time
最有名的就是關於時空的分類
He said time can be used in minutes
他說時間可以用分
seconds, days, years, etc.
秒、時日、天年等等
plan a computational
規劃一個可以計算
independent events
獨立出來的事件
This is no longer the experience of the event
這再也不是事件的經歷了
For example, we often say
比方說我們常會說
That evening when the gorge was full of sky
那天傍晚踩峽滿天的時候
no you tell me now
不 你現在要告訴我
what time am i now
我現在是幾點幾分
it's totally different
這是完全不一樣的
perception of time
對時間的感知
And another example is the space
而另外比方說空間
no longer through the relationship of things
再也不是透過事物的關係
figuratively symbolic or religious sanctity
比喻象徵或宗教上的神聖性
let's talk about space
來談空間
For example, the most famous
比方說最有名的是
Perspective to talk about space
透視法來談空間
If we talk about space from perspective
如果從透視來談空間
It is the same as anything that is familiar with everyday religious values
它跟任何是熟日常宗教價值
Actually it doesn't matter
其實也就沒有關係
every time i'm flying
每次我在坐飛機的時候
I like to see its route map the most
最喜歡看它那個航線圖
Then you'll find out that
然後你就會發現說
Oh, this is how Jinweidu drew it
喔 金尾度是這樣畫的
Oh so we are here now
喔 原來我們現在在這裡
wait to get there
等一下到那裡
You will find that this is an event composed of spacers and lines
你會發現這是隔子和線條構成的事件
Here is a chart of the golden scale
這是一個金密尺度的圖表
Indeed, people pass through this partition line
的確 人透過這個隔子線條
Conquered or rediscovered the universe
征服或者是重新發現了宇宙
But should we be careful
可是我們是不是也要小心謹慎
Conversely, people accept that these squares and lines
反過來人接受這些方格跟線條的
arrangement and arrangement
安排與擺佈
This is when polygamy becomes a problem
這時候多異性成為問題
Obviously in 1911
很明顯的在1911年
General Encyclopedia Xingda Dictionary published by Huang Ren
黃人出版的普通百科興大詞典
can be seen inside
裡面可以看到
General Encyclopedia Xingda Dictionary
普通百科興大詞典呢
It is also a very important reference book for us
對我們來說也是非常重要的一部參考書
but it's very cooked
但是它非常熟
There is only one left in Taiwan, there should be only two or three left in the world
台灣只剩一部 應該全球應該只剩兩三部
Then this one is now hidden in the National Library of Taichung
那這一部現在藏在臺中的國立圖書館
In this general encyclopedia new dictionary
在這個普通百科新大詞典裡面
It mainly explains all new disciplines
它主要是解釋一切新學科
So it's called a discipline, like a discipline manual
所以它叫學科 像學科手冊一樣
For example, psychology, literature, gold studies, etc.
比如說心理學 文學 金學等等之類的
that's interesting
那可是很有意思的是
It specifically says in the preface
它在序文裡面特別說
Leishu in traditional Chinese
傳統漢語裡面的類書 字書
These are too hesitant and vague, we don't want them
這些都太猶豫模糊了 我們都不要了
at this point in time
在這個時間點上
Definition and ambiguity become differences that must be chosen
定解跟多義 成為必須取捨的分歧
You'll find it categorized and numbered by stroke
你會發現它分門別類 而且按筆劃數
Sort by number of strokes
按筆劃數來分類
In classifying this mainstream
在分門別類這個主流
Originally the mainstream of the development of Western natural history
本來是西方博物學發展的主流
Then under this classification
那這個分門別類底下
we have to be careful what it might lose
我們要小心它可能失去什麼
For example, it may lose its overall structure
比方說它可能失去整體性的結構
I give one
我舉一個
one example
一個例子
In the whole ordinary Hundred Stars Big Magnetic Spot
在整部普通百顆星大磁點裡面
There is no star magnetic stripe
並沒有星這個磁條
that he put us through the stars might think
那他把我們通過星可能會想到的
feeling, feeling
感覺啊 感情啊
It's all in psychology
這些都放在心理學裡面
And specifically
而且特別說明
through natural science
透過自然科學
to understand feelings or feelings
就可以了解感情或者是感覺
But when we use star in Chinese
但是我們在漢語使用星的時候
what he might be involved in
他可能牽涉什麼
I'll just name a few
我隨便舉幾個
The star may be related to the star system
星可能跟星制有關
Xing may be related to Wen Xing
星可能跟文星有關
Because we know writers are stars of literature
因為我們知道文者是星之文業
when you speak and write
當你發言書寫的時候
In fact, it is expressed through text
其實是透過文來表達
That's why we call Wenxing
所以我們叫文星
Then in science
那另外在理學裡面
We know there is also astrology
我們知道也有星學
But when the magnetic stripe of the star is removed
可是當把星這個磁條去掉的時候
This series of connections is gone.
這一系列的聯繫就都沒有了
you can't see at all
你完全看不到
Also in 1915
另外呢 在1915年
Hu Shi is a man who sees the extreme
胡適是一個見極履極的人
What about after he went to America to study?
那他到美國留學以後呢
Because he wants to teach Chinese characters
因為他要教授漢字
then he said
然後他就說
we should have grammar
我們應該要有文法
Otherwise it is very difficult to teach
否則是非常難以教授的
So the previous sentence
所以前面的那一句話
to specify to be obvious
要規定 要明顯意見
It is not easy to determine
要確定不易
It is from this experience of teaching foreign languages
就是從這個教外國語的經驗來的
So we can find from this data that
所以我們從這個資料可以發現
He mainly focuses on foreign language teaching
他主要是著重外語教學
with Chinese education
而跟國文教育
In fact, there should be a difference
其實是應該有區別的
This is what I just said
這個就是我剛剛講的
There are a group of people like Hu Mingfu in China
中國有一批人像胡明富
or Ren Shuyong
或者是任淑勇
In order to emulate him, he was influenced by the American Science magazine
他為了效法受到美國的Science雜誌的影響
Therefore, Science magazine was also established in China.
所以在中國也辦了Science科學雜誌
in this magazine
在這個雜誌裡面
Hu Shi's article on punctuation marks
胡適的講標點符號的那篇文章
Published in January 1916
在1916年的正月發表
That is what he wrote in 1915
也就是他在1915年寫的
Then this article is called "On Sentence Fighting and Character Symbols"
那這篇文章叫《論句鬥及文字符號》
What he's talking about is actually the punctuation we use today.
他講的其實就是我們現在用的標點符號
You can find this issue inside the drug tomb
你可以發現這一期的藥墓裡面
let's say algebra
比方說代數
Then this scientific spirit talks about machine skin eggs and so on
然後這個科學精神論機器膚卵等等
It's very very scientific and mechanical
這是非常非常科學跟機械式
or a technical magazine
或技術性的一個一本雜誌
What about the characters and symbols of Hu Shi's drama dramas?
那胡適論劇鬥集文字符號呢
It's actually a small part of all his ideas.
其實是他所有設想裡面的一個小部分
Of course it is also an important part
當然也是一個重要的部分
He once said that if you sort out old books,
他曾經說如果你要整理古書的話
Be sure to segment and punctuate
一定要分段要標點
And it should be written like a mind
而且要像心思的寫法
get together
一聚一行
Then one by one
然後一張一段
What about this view?
那這樣的看法呢
In fact, Hu Shi is a sword fighter
其實胡適是一個劍擊履歧
Like I said he's very, very passionate to push a lot of things
像我剛說的他非常非常有熱情來推動很多事
So we can find
所以我們就可以發現
In 1916, he published On Judou Ji Character Symbols
1916年他有論劇鬥集文字符號
I just said that
這我剛剛講過了
Then successively
然後這中間陸續的
Especially in 1920
尤其在1920年
Many people let the Ministry of Education announce the implementation of mind punctuation
很多人讓教育部公布實施了心事標點符號
Then Tongling National Primary School Grade 12
然後通令國民小學12年級
To change the language style of the national language
要改國文語體文
Abolish ancient Chinese
廢除古文
And finally more importantly
然後最後更重要的是
He finished a very long article
他完成了一篇很長的文章
two or three articles
是兩三篇文章
finally published together
最後合起來出版
On the Reform of Guoyu Grammar
叫國語文法改論
Since then, he has promoted the vernacular movement
從此他把他所推行的白話文運動
to a more hierarchical
推向一個比較有層次
and
而且
implemented through government measures
透過政府的措施來執行
So if we're talking about a literary revolution now
所以如果我們現在要談文學革命
We can't actually ignore
我們其實是不能忽略
Take the forty or fifty years from 1970 to 1920
以把70年到1920這個四五十年間
On the one hand, there is a world revolution that adds new words and new themes
一方面有加入新語詞新題材的世界革命
But more importantly, emphasize
可是更重要的是強調
We have a literary revolution in grammar and punctuation
我們有文法跟標點符號的文學革命
And if you go back to the source
而這當中如果你追本溯源
It is related to the technological civilization of a certain technological system
他跟某一種技術體系的科技文明是有關係的
A Value Framework Based on Scientific Machines
以科學機器為主的一個價值框架
he compared to the traditional
他相對於傳統
re-established the modern method of reading composition
就重新定立了現代讀書作文的方法
Also opened Chinese
同時也開啟了漢語
and a new page in psychological self-reflection
和心思學自我反省的新的一頁
often we hear
常常我們會聽到說
Literary Controversy Literal Controversy
文白之爭 文白之爭
But in fact, these four words are too simplified
可是其實這四個字是太過簡化了
why
為什麼呢
Because we actually missed a lot of thinking and discussion in the middle
因為我們其實遺漏了中間很多思考和論述
let's say the first
比方說第一個
What I'm talking about is based on these few items
一下我講的就根據這幾項
Let's say the first grammar
比方說第一個文法
We feel we didn't spell a word
我們覺得我們沒有拼一文字
At that time, a group of people felt that this was our shame.
當時一批人覺得這是我們的愧缺
So we should look to English grammar
所以我們應該向英語文法看起
we need grammar
我們要有文法
But there are no Chinese characters in English grammar
但是沒有英語文法的漢字
How will it continue to develop in the future
它將來要怎麼繼續發展
This is the question that people continued to think about at that time
這是當時人繼續思考的問題
What if there is no English grammar, Chinese characters?
如果沒有英語文法 漢字怎麼辦
second rhetorical
第二個 修詞
you might ask
你可能會問說
Well, if grammar is so important, with English grammar
好 如果文法這麼重要有了英語文法
why do we need rhetoric
我們為什麼還需要修詞
Why were there so many fake grammar names back then
當時為什麼有那麼多假文法之名
Some Discussions about Rhetorical Words
講修詞的一些相關論述
Well, if you have Wen French
好 如果有了文法語
Why do we still have the so-called semantics of rhetoric
修詞我們為什麼還有有所謂的意義學
Hope to develop into a discipline
希望推展成一門學科
Why is there still semantics?
為什麼還有意義學呢
because they want to ask how meaning comes about
因為他們要問意義是怎麼產生的
This is of course related to the most fundamental problem of language
這當然跟語言文字最根本的問題有關
Finally, I will talk about the issues of polygamy and modernity.
那最後我會談談多異性跟現代性的問題
Okay, first point about grammar
好 關於文法第一點
At that time, of course, the first book about Chinese characters
當時當然第一本關於漢字的什麼
It is Wentong, it mainly uses classical Chinese
是文通 它以文言文為主
But the first grammar book on the national language was
但是第一本關於國語的文法是
Li Jingxi's New Mandarin Grammar
李景熙的新駐國語文法
published in 1924
在1924年就出版了
After publication, it caused a lot of discussion
出版以後引起非常非常多的討論
In 1942, Liao Shuqian made a summary
到了1942年廖淑芊做總結
in the process
在這過程當中
There are at least two key points in the discussion of Chinese grammar
對於中國語文法的討論至少有兩個重點
The first point is
第一個重點是
when we talk about Chinese grammar
當我們談論中國語的文法的時候
It is true that it is not necessary and impossible to imitate the West
的確不必也不能模仿西方
He didn't say no need
他對沒有說不需要
No need to imitate Xifa
不必其實很難模仿西法
we must break
我們必須破除
Limitations between polytheory or word theory
聚論或者詞論之間的侷限
For example, what is word theory
比方說詞論是什麼
Are you singular or plural
你是單數還是多數
Are you present tense or ongoing tense
你是現在式還是進行式
Then Jufa is presiding over verbs, numerals, etc.
然後巨法就是主持動詞數詞等等
it is we going to break this
它是我們要破除這個
Pay attention to English grammar
對於用英語文法來講究
Chinese grammar has such a recognition
中國語的文法有這樣的體認
In fact, we only need to talk
其實我們只要講
think for example
想到比方說
Airframe, Maodian, Moon, Man-Machine, Banqiao, Frost
機身、毛電、月、人機、板橋、霜
This is completely inconsistent with the giant law of Western English
這完全不符合西洋英文的巨法
Withered vines, mice, faint cliffs
枯藤、老鼠、昏崖
it doesn't fit at all
這完全也不符合
But in China it is a sentence
可是在中國就是一個句子
Another second point
另外第二點
Lee Kyung Hee expressed it in a convex solution
李景熙他是以凸解方式表示
Jufa should be divided into various parts and functions
巨法應該分成種種的部件跟職務
what is his mission
他的任務是什麼
This is a theoretical sequence
這是一個理論的次序
However, many discussions at that time put forward this
可是當時很多論述提出這個
there is a breach
有一個破口就是
where is the order of literature
那文學的次序在哪裡
What is a concrete representation of the image
什麼是可以具體的形象的表示
Sentences with thoughts and emotions of things
事物思想情感的句子
That is the lively element in the article
那才是文章裡面生動活潑的要素
This reminds us of Li Qingzhao's
這會讓我們想起李清照的
This search for secrets is in a cold mood
這個尋尋 秘密 冷冷 心情
seven seven miserable seven seven
七七 慘慘七七
you will find out
你會發現呢
It's totally ungrammatical
這裡面完全不符合文法
But these seven sets of spy characters at the beginning
可是這些一開頭的七組諜字
the pain of ruining his family
就把他家破人亡的沉痛
push to the top
一口氣推到最高點
Therefore, traditional calligraphy
所以書情傳統的
Everyone knows Mr. Yang Mude
大家都知道的楊木德老師
Mr. Chen Shixiang thinks
陳世湘先生就認為
This is the most winged moment
這是最富翼翼的時刻
When you speak out these seven sets of spy sentences
當你把這個七組諜句講出來的時候
so from here
所以從這裡呢
It makes sense to reflect on these two points
這兩點的反省是有道理的
These two reflections are accompanied by
這兩點的反省同時伴隨著
late nineteenth century to early twentieth century
十九世紀末到二十世紀初
Some phenomena of rhetoric discussed in the name of grammar
假借文法之名而討論修辭的一些現象
often someone will say
常常有人會說
i know rhetoric
我知道修辭學
it was 1932
那不是就是1932年
Is Mr. Chen Wangdao's rhetoric extraordinary?
陳旺道先生的修辭學發凡嗎
But I want to emphasize here
但是我在這裡要特別強調
It's not just about the founding of a discipline
這不只是關於一個學科的成立而已
In fact, if we compare grammar with rhetoric
其實如果我們把文法跟修辭並比來看
You know that rhetoric has a purpose
你就知道修辭有它發展的初衷
and most importantly
以及最重要的目的
The first point
第一點
When Grammars Don't Talk About Categories of Meaning
當文法不再談論意義的類別
When making words and plots related to it
和它相關的造詞構劇謀篇的時候
So who is going to talk about the complex relationship between self-containment and meaning?
那麼誰來談自具跟意義之間的複雜關係
rhetoric
修辭
Second point
第二點
When Grammar Becomes a Measure of Parts of Speech
當文法成為衡量詞類
Or when the play structure of the active soldier
或者是主動兵的劇法結構的時候
Who comes outside the standard form of this expression
誰來在這個表達形式的標準格式之外
Reconsider Chinese or Chinese
重新考量中國語或者漢語
The Rhetoric of Diverse Possibilities in Emotional Expression
在情感表達上多樣的可能性修辭學
so i remember we were in college
所以我記得我們在大學
The Department of National Taiwan University seems to have no rhetoric
台大中的系好像沒有修辭學了
But I know there are many teachers
但是我知道還有很多老師
made important contributions to rhetoric
對修辭學做出很重要的貢獻
then i felt
那時候我就覺得
In fact, we need a new view on rhetoric
其實我們對修辭學要有新的看法
If from late Qing Dynasty to early Ming Dynasty
如果從晚清明初
Corresponding to Western English Grammar
對應西方的尤其英語文法
when it strikes
來襲的時候
The rhetoric of how we respond
我們是怎麼回應的修辭學
had its important place in that century electricity
有它在那個世紀電力的重要地位
What is the Grammar of Change
什麼叫變革的語法
Can Grammar Be Changed?
語法可以變革嗎
Here we will see a book
在這裡我們就會看到一本書
Very important is Tang Yue's rhetorical revolution in 1923
非常重要是1923年唐月的修辭革
Everyone sees that this is 1923
大家看到這是1923年
Earlier than Chen Wangdao's rhetoric was published in 1932
比陳旺道的修辭學發凡1932年更早
Tangyue is not someone else
唐月不是別人
She is a good friend of Hu Shi at Cornell University
她是在康乃爾大學胡適的好朋友
Youth witnesses how she started
青年見證她怎麼開始
Her vernacular or literary revolution
她的白話文或者是文學革命
The three words of psychology we are talking about now
我們現在說的心理學三個字
Tangyue too
也是唐月
It was his translation that made the final decision
是他翻譯而定案的
He later really became a very important psychologist
他後來就真的變成一個很重要的心理學家
But he is this Hu family, whether it is the piano-pushing literary revolution
但是他是這個胡氏不管是推琴文學革命
or sorting out the history of the country
或者是整理國故
very important partner
非常重要的夥伴
Then he has a book called Xiuci
那他有一本叫修詞隔
grammar of change
就談到變革的語法
The so-called grammar of change is
所謂變革的語法就是
unusual everyday tone
不是尋常日常的語氣
He said that in rhetoric or composition
他說在修詞學或者是作文裡面
Using the original text is not just a matter of conforming to grammatical guidelines
使用原文字不是只要要求符合文法準則就好了
He says it's just the cognitive function of understanding communication
他說那只是可以理解溝通的認知作用
But there is a more important role
但是還有一個更重要的作用
is to elicit an emotional effect
是要引發情緒上的作用
In particular, he gives a lot of examples that are all about metaphors
他尤其舉了很多的例子都是關於比喻的
The example of this metaphor is very interesting
這個比喻的例子非常有趣
is what we use now
是我們現在常用
like one of his hearts
比方說他的一顆心
but why say
可是為什麼要講成
his square heart
他的一顆方心
Fangfang is the way of dividing squares
方方是分方的方式
Fang is often used to describe a woman's admiration or inner state of mind
方常常用來形容女子愛慕或內在的心境
Why say a square star
為什麼要說一顆方星
It's better not to say one star
而不是講一顆星就好了
Did you notice an important difference between
這當中你有沒有發現有很重要的差別是
He turned the metaphor into a metaphor
他把比喻變成本喻了
it was just a metaphor
就是本來只是比喻
square star is a metaphor
方星是一個比喻詞
But he became a metaphor
可是他變成本喻了
We often say Fang Xing
常常我們說方星
or be speechless
或者是不講言而無性
tell the truth
要講實言
The truth is that you have broken your trust
實言就是你失信於人
why tell the truth
為什麼講實言
In fact, it is only a metaphor or a metaphor
實本來只是一個隱喻或比喻
Now it's a metaphor
現在變成本喻了
not to mention
更不用說
For example, anthropomorphic
比方說用擬人法來講
wind blowing and falling
風吹與降
Blow is our exit
吹是我們出口
blow the breath out of your mouth
把口中的氣吹出來
In addition, descending is from a place where the mountain is relatively high.
另外降就是從山比較高的地方
to a lower place
到比較低的地方
This is an anthropomorphic metaphor
這是擬人法的比喻
But now we also say
可是現在我們也這樣講
the wind is blowing
風吹起來了
In addition, you can also use nature to talk about people
另外你也可以用大自然來講人
For example we often say
比方說我們常常說
the person's thoughts or thoughts
這個人的思慮或思想
very profound
非常深遠
The depth originally refers to the depth of the water
那個深本來是講水的深淺
That distance was originally a telescope for talking about the road
那個遠本來是講道路的遠鏡
But we use natural phenomena to talk about human beings.
可是我們把自然的現象拿來講人
so what about these metaphors
所以這些比喻呢
It's almost become intentional
幾乎都變成本意了
let's say you want to think deeply
比方說你要深思
pondering itself
深思本身
is a metaphor to become
就是一個比喻來而變成
Situations where everyday spoken English can be used
日常口語可以使用的狀況
This is probably what he said
這個大概是他講的
inside the grammar of change
變革的語法裡面
There are many examples that we still use today
非常多我們現在還在用的例子
If we look at the grammar of change
如果從變革的語法來看
Then the part of speech in the grammar
那麼文法中的詞類劃分
really only marks a part of things
的確只能標明事物的一部分
Let's say we define the word as an adjective
比方說我們限定這個詞就是形容詞
Then he can only express the nature
那他就是只能表示性質
This word is the progressive tense
這個詞呢是進行式
he said action
他就表示行動
This is only part of the representation
這個是表示部分而已
But we clearly found
可是我們明明發現
so much deep understanding
那麼多深同意境
The situation of multiple variants of one yin or multiple variants of one word
一陰多異或一字多異的狀況
these kinds of
這些這些種種
Between sound and concept, between shape and meaning
在聲音與概念之間 字形與意義之間
You will find that there is not only one correspondence
你會發現它不是只有一種對應
definitely not just a correspondence
絕對不會只是一種對應
If this is the case
如果是這樣
In fact, it has already exceeded the norms of parts of speech.
它其實早就超出了 詞類的規範了
So the linguist Zhang Shilu at that time
所以當時的語言學家張世露
He also translated some of Gao Benhan's Chinese works
他也曾經翻譯高本漢的一些漢語的著作
he just said pointing
他就說 指
The word finger turned out to be your toe
指這個字原來是你的腳趾
That is, he turned out to be a hieroglyph, toe
就是他原來是一個象形字 腳趾
He said what does the word toe conjure up?
他說腳趾這個字讓人聯想到哪些呢
Toe-up, toe-in, middle toe, toe, etc.
舉趾 進趾 中趾 足趾等等這些
What does this mean about the toes?
這些關於趾的意義呢
There is no way to only see the word toe
是沒有辦法只用看到趾這個字
It can be judged by determining the role of its part of speech in the play
就定好它的詞類在劇中的作用就可以判斷的
You have to deliberate and identify from the context
你必須從上下文裡面來反覆推敲辯認
That is to say, in the process of writing Chinese or interpreting Chinese,
也就是說在書寫漢語或詮釋漢語的過程裡面
Aware of the diversity of Chinese
意識到漢語多異性
thus presenting Chinese or Chinese
從而呈現漢語或中國語
Maximum possibility in heterogeneous expression
在異異表達上最大的可能性
It is why people at that time had to think hard, Jin Si, deep thinking
是當時人為什麼要苦思 金思 熟思
very important topic
很重要的一個重要的議題
Then we will progress to our heterology
接著就會進展到我們的異異學
you may find it strange
你可能會覺得很奇怪
rhetoric is a science
修辭學是一門學問
But why did they promote the so-called heterodoxism at that time?
可是當時為什麼要推行所謂的異異學呢
This was also in 1933
這同樣也就在1933年而已
Different and Different Studies is a book written by Li Anzhai
異異學是李安宅所寫的一本書
In a moment I'll explain why he wrote the book
等一下我會說明為什麼他要寫這本書
he talked about
他就談到說
We must pay at least a few percent attention to the application of language and characters
我們至少要有幾成注意語言文字的應用
First, grammar or logic is currently being promoted enthusiastically
第一 文法或邏輯是目前大家很熱烈在推廣
But he actually paid little attention to the relationship between language and thought.
可是他其實很少注意語言跟思想的關係
At the same time, he pays little attention to the relationship between language and external things.
同時他也很少注意語言跟外在事物的關係
in graph theory
在圖表理論上
What's more, he doesn't care
更重要的是他也不關注
what readers and listeners say about language
讀者聽者會對語言所陳述
what kind of attitude
抱持什麼樣的態度
I think the last point is very important
最後這一點我覺得特別特別重要
I think right now we're working on a lot
我想現在我們在研究很多
Whether it is the study of psychology or linguistics
不管是心理學關於語言學的研究
neuroscience research
神經科學的研究
Or even the AI ​​artificial intelligence we're driving now
或甚至我們現在推動的 AI 人工智慧
this is actually very very important
這其實是非常非常重要
It is also a very hard part
也是非常需要努力的部分
This last point actually tells us that
最後這一點其實是告訴我們說
our psychology
我們的心理
all the process
所有的過程
Whether it's emotions, thoughts, emotions, etc.
不管是情感思想情緒等等
will not be all under the control of symbols
都不會只是全部在符號的支配底下
we just have to think
我們只要想想
Even we often say that the meaning is beyond words
甚至我們常常會說意在言外不可言喻
So it's not just the grammar that doesn't regulate our
所以不只是文法不能規範我們
even many words can not express
甚至很多言喻不能表達的
So what about meaning generation?
所以面對意義的產生呢
Li Anzhai wrote Semantics
李安宅就寫了意義學
this is very important
這本非常重要的
Then Li Anzhai was affected by the responsibility
那李安宅是受責影響
In fact, it was influenced by I.A. Richer
其實是受I.A. Richer的影響
this person is not someone else
這個人不是別人
He was actually considered to be one of the ten groups of New Criticism
他其實被認為是後來新批評的十組
Then he once gave lectures in China from 1929 to 1931
那麼他曾經在1929年到1931年在中國講學
He has a very very famous article
他有一篇非常非常有名的文章
It's called Minnin of meaning
叫做Minnin of meaning
This one looks weird
這個看起來很奇怪的一個一篇
In fact, he directly
其實他直接講
The word Minnin
Minnin這個字
He analyzed at least 16 meanings
他分析出來至少有16種意義
That is to say, the word Minnin is not only available to you by looking it up in the dictionary.
也就是說Minnin這個字不是只有你查字典就可以得到的
He speaks the word Minnin
他講說Minnin這個字
For example, his station in the system is the most important
比方說他在系統裡面的站最重要的
We say he has point
我們說他具有point
he has meaning
他具有意義
Or it is related to our future expectations
或者是說他跟我們未來的預期相關
we say he makes sense
我們說他有意義
or affirmation of my past efforts
或者是說對我過去的努力的肯定
Or I imagine my acceptance first
或者我先設想我的受化
my audience
我的聽眾
The part he wants to know the most
他經歷最想要知道的那部分
i think he makes sense
我認為他有意義
So in this article he is
所以在這篇文章裡面他在
He actually put forward a very important theory
他其實提出了一個很重要的理論
it's about context
就是關於語境
Theory about context
關於context的理論
in this article
在這一篇文章裡面
He talks about grammar
他談到說文法
often just sees itself as a normative system
常常只是把自己視為一種規範的體系
Analyze the so-called correct usage
分析所謂正確的用法
He said that this is actually a matter of minor details.
他說這個其實是次要的細節的問題
he gave an example
他就舉了一個例子
He said that a French scholar
他說法國的一個學者
Brunaut
Brunaut
Already shouted in 1903
1903年就已經大聲疾呼
part of speech
我們要放棄所謂詞類
That is, the teaching or research method of distinguishing verb names, etc.
也就是分別動詞名字等等的教學或研究法
There is a very interesting sentence
有一句話很有意思
He said we must make up our minds
他說我們必須下定決心
thought-based
設計出以思想為依據
rather than the study of linguistics based on signs
而不再是以符號為依據的語言學的研究
Then what about I.A. Richards
後來呢 I.A. Richards
He actually published a book in the 1930s
他其實在1930年代出了一本書
Called Science and Poetry
叫Science and Poetry
a very important book
一本很重要的書
He later used this book as a basis
後來他以這本書為基礎呢
published another
出版了另外一本
The Definitive Edition is Poetry and Sciences
《真定版》是 Poetry and Sciences
in this book
在這本書裡面
two languages
他就分出兩種語言
He said that there is a scientific language
他說有一種叫 scientific language
is the language of science
是科學的語言
the language of pure science
這種純科學的語言
I hope he is not affected by personal emotions
希望他不受個人情感的影響
There is also no need to consider the subject referred to by the symbol
也不需要考慮藉由符號所指稱的課題
Can the music listener be restored?
能不能復原樂聽者的
sensory perception
感官 知覺狀態
he said it doesn't need
他說這不需要
But if it's summoning language
但是如果是召喚性的語言
This was in the 1930s
這個當時在 1930 年代
translate it into emotional language
把它翻成情感的語言
For comparison with science
為了跟科學的對照
But I think it might be better to summon
但是我想應該也許是召喚比較好
in the calling language
在召喚性的語言裡面
but through the rhythm rhyme
卻要透過節奏 押韻
and past rhymes experience
還有過去的韻律 經驗
For example, you read a lot of ancient poems
比方說你古詩念了很多
You immediately know where to break the sentence with these seven characters
你馬上知道這七個字要在哪裡斷句
etc.
等等
In the memory of the situation
還有情境回憶中
emotion born of association
因為聯想而生的情感
then calls out on the reader
那麼會在讀者身上召喚出
emotional longing feeling
情緒 渴望 感覺
or an attitude
或者是一種態度
He said we should have two languages
他說我們應該有兩種語言
not just one language
不要只有一種語言
He did not deny the language of the preceding science
他沒有否定前面的科學的語言
But he thinks there should be two languages
但是他覺得要有兩種語言
So if we find that from China
所以如果我們發現從中國
Heard the development of rhetoric from grammar to semantics
從文法學中間聽過修辭學到意義學的發展
Reachers' point of view is actually very important to pay attention to
Reachers的看法其實有非常值得重視的關鍵性
First, he clearly pointed out the grammar
第一他明白指出文法
not the main way to understand semantics
不是理解語意的主要途徑
is a way
是一個途徑
but not the main way
但是不是主要的途徑
Instead, close reading of the text
而應該以細讀文本
to replace standard grammar teaching
來取代標準的文法的教學方式
the second
第二個
say or write
說或寫者
In fact, their psychological structure is very complex.
其實他們的心理結構都是非常分雜的
In this ambiguous and contextual poetic language
這個多義性而脈絡性的詩語中
Only then can we be able to distinguish the differences in the expression of poetic and scientific language
才能夠區分出詩語科學語言表述上的差異
he said the poet
他說詩人
Often we have a poem in our hearts
常常我們有一句詩在心裡
will return to the reciprocating protagonist
就會回返往復的主角
several years
好幾年
The playwright is deeply moved by people's affection
這位劇師在人的情深異動上
will have such an important role
會有這麼重要的作用
because he first used the movement and sound of his own words
因為他先用自詞的運動和聲音
to pique our interest
來激動我們的興趣
What is the movement and sound of Zici?
什麼叫自詞的運動和聲音呢
We can say that the main thing is actually
我們可以說主要其實就是
structure and rhythm
結構和節奏
how did he get together
他是怎麼構聚的
Why is this word put in front
這個字為什麼要放在前面
Why is that word put at the back?
那個字為什麼要放在後面
etc.
等等
It's what piques our interest
這些才會激動我們的興趣
And what about this deep emotion?
而這個情深異動呢
It is indeed a science of logic
確實是講究邏輯的科學
factors to be ruled out
所要極力排除的因素
Ritchard immediately communicated with the alien
Ritchard立即與異學
Discuss differences in language use in poetic science
討論詩語科學在語言使用上的差異
Obviously since 1920
明顯跟1920年以來
What about the trend of discussing Mandarin grammar?
討論國語文法的風潮呢
There are some discrepancies
有一些出入
because he turned
因為他轉向了
Meaningful expression based on meaning or emotion
以意義或感情為主的表義方式
What is the significance of this in the whole zeitgeist
這個在整個時代思潮上的意義是什麼
Grammar
因為他明顯讓文法為主
beyond standard discourse
理準的論述之外
reveals the development of another Chinese language
揭示了另外一種中國語的發展
mind language
和漢語心思學的心思語
Of course, in the end we talked about how to modernize
當然最後講到如何現代
How to be modern is not the only direction I just talked about
如何現代不是只有我剛剛講的一種方向
On the Modernization Project of Chinese Characters Since the Literary Revolution
在文學革命以來論及漢字的現代化工程
has many angles
是有非常多角度的
For example, we want to pinyinize
比方說我們要拼音化
Acousticization
搭聽化
we want to simplify
我們要簡化
Even if we abolish Chinese characters
甚至我們就廢除漢字好了
Let Chinese characters combine with civilization and science
讓漢字跟文明和科學結合起來
There are many differences in the location of these calligraphy
這些書法所在多有非常分歧
Perhaps the most famous example is Lin Yutang's Bright Typewriter
最著名的一個例子可能是林宇棠的明快打字機
It's very clear and fast
就很明白清楚而且很快捷
In this Chinese character typewriter
在這個漢字打字機裡面
He is a part through romanization and strokes
他是透過羅馬拼音跟筆劃的部件
The part of the stroke is not the hand, the hand is meaningful
那個筆劃的部件不是部手,部手是有意義的
The parts of this stroke don't necessarily make sense
這個筆劃的部件不見得有意義
he
他
The method used is the number let's say
使用的方法是號碼比方說
Mr. Wang Yunwu's four-corner number
王雲武先生的四角號碼
He used this number to further modify the four-corner number
他用這個號碼 四角號碼進一步改裝
He said that a word only needs four numbers
他說一個字只要有四個號碼就好
These four numbers are not in stroke order
這個四個號碼不是用筆順
is the stroke that starts with the two tallest ones on the upper left
是用左上最高的那兩個開始的筆劃
with the two strokes on the lower right
跟右下那兩個筆劃
to form four numbers
來構成四個號碼
then on the ice cube typewriter
然後在冰塊打字機上
Lay the parts up
把這些部件鋪設起來
so you type
所以你打字
In fact, it is combined with mechanized stroke configuration
其實跟機械化的筆劃配置就結合在一起
Professor of Golden Animals at Yale University
耶魯大學的金畜教授
He once had a book about Lin Yutang's typewriter
他曾經有一本書來講林語堂的打字機
He said that this is the meaning system of Chinese characters
他說這是把漢字的表義系統
system of conversions to letters
轉換成字母的系統
is the Western alphabet system
就是西方字母的系統
This is a very interesting study
這是一個非常有意思的研究
It also tells us that Chinese characters have the possibility of diverse development
也告訴我們其實漢字有多樣性的發展的可能
But this development is worth thinking about here
但是這個發展值得思考的地方在這裡
If Chinese characters are pinyinized or symbolized
漢字如果拼音化或者是符號化
That is to say, Chinese characters are like Western letters.
也就是把漢字是如西洋的字母一般
It can be constructed and spelled out the speaking voice arbitrarily
可以任意構造拼讀出說話的聲音
But there is no way to spell it out
但是沒有辦法把它這個拼音
with font, meaning
跟字形、字義
so that speaking organisms connect
乃至於說話的有機體連結起來
what's the problem
這當中出現一個什麼問題
That is, it ignores the basic nature of Chinese culture
就是它忽略了漢語文化的基本的本質是什麼
When I construct such a set of Chinese
當我構造這樣一套漢語的時候
what is my lust
我的色想的根本是什麼
is a person with complex perception
是一個感知複雜的人才對
Instead of the pinyin system for the convenience of quick and simple communication
而不是只是為了便利快速簡單溝通的拼音系
In fact, through a person with complex perception
其實是透過一個感知複雜的人
to construct a Chinese system
來建構一個漢語的體系
become the essence of culture
成為文化的本質
In fact, the question of modernity
其實關於現代性的問題
We most often think of Fockeau's word thing
我們最常想起來應該是Fockeau的詞語物
He said that since the 17th century
他說17世紀以來
We often record, classify, configure
我們常常透過記錄、分類、配置
constructed horizon
所建構的視野
Then this field of view
那麼這個視野
it's called the order of the modern sight
它稱為現代視線的秩序
what does this contain
這包含什麼
this contains a lot
這包含很多
Museums we frequent
我們常常進的博物館
natural history we see
我們看的博物學
The financial analysis report we look at
我們看的財務分析報表
The libraries we looked at Department stores
我們看的圖書館 百貨公司
and what we talked about today
還有我們今天講的
Grammar and Disciplinary Institutions for Knowledge and Language
關於知識和語言的文法與學科建制
These establishments are classified into
這些建制進入了分類
juxtaposed or cut in a field of view
並列或者是切割的一個視野之中
This is the modern line of sight, the underground line of sight
這個是屬於現代的視線 地下的視野
but
但是
did you find out
你有沒有發現
This is the existence of knowledge prior to man
這是知識先於人的存在
The construction of this knowledge system
這個知識體系的建構
prehuman existence
先於人的存在
it manipulates our look
它擺佈了我們的看
what we see what we think
我們所看 所思 所想
feel
所感受
So dominate people
所以支配了人
So human knowledge
所以為人的知識
Hawko even said very pessimistically
霍寇甚至非常悲觀地說
This is an inhuman study of the humanities
這是一個非人的人文科學研究
inhuman is possible
非人就是可能
The essence or nature of non-official people
非官人的本質或本性
here
在此
The last sentence of the book of words
詞語物這本書的最後一句
it is a little mournful in nature to say
它是有一點哀悼的性質說
people will be erased
人將被抹去
like a face in the sand by the sea
如同海邊沙地上的一張臉
He said there is no way
他說人再也沒有辦法
exist in the essence and nature of man
在人的本質和本性上存在
If we have been using the framework of modern vision
如果我們一直用現代視線的框架
Let's see what people and the world say
來看人跟世界的話
In fact, the problem of heterosexual Chinese
其實把多異性的漢語的問題
Putting back the architecture of the modern sight where the grammar resides
放回文法所在的現代視線的架構
You will find that heterosexuality is definitely not just a language problem
你就會發現多異性絕對不是只是一個語言問題
It's not just a matter of language
不是一個單純的語言問題
It is more a question of how modern
更是一個如何現代的問題
From the point of view of modernity
在現代性的角度裡面
We found that there are many
我們發現有非常多
Especially since the so-called scientific enlightenment, rationalism
尤其從所謂科學啟蒙 理性主義以來
We will emphasize that we are going to modern
我們會強調我們要走向現代
We are going to mechanize
我們要走向機械化
This seems to be a very progressive orientation
這個好像非常進步的取向
But if you look at the original culture
可是如果你看當初從文化
grammatical rhetoric down to these discussions of polysexuality
文法修辭一直到多異性的這些討論
you will find
你就會發現
It turns out that in the language revolution of Chinese
原來漢語的語言革命裡面
Has a flipped modern angle
有一個翻轉現代的角度
Inside this angle that flips modern events
在這個翻轉現代事件的角度裡面
it provides another mode of feeling
它提供了另一種感覺模式
or another affective construct
或另一種情感結構
for example
比方說
We're about to talk about Zhu Zhiqing
我們就要談到朱志清了
Zhu Zhiqing says
朱志清說
we really need a new language
我們的確要有一種新語言
So where do we start with this new language?
那這個新語言要從哪裡著手呢
Zhu Zhiqing is also I.A. Richard
朱志清同時是 I.A. Richard
Colleagues who were teaching in China at the time
當時在中國講學的同事
He is from the Department of Chinese and Richard is from the Department of Foreign Languages.
他是中文系 Richard 在外文系
So Zhu Zhiqing once wrote an article called
所以朱志清曾經有一篇文章叫
Versatile examples
詩多異舉例
I guess it has something to do with the influence of I.A. Richard
我想跟 I.A. Richard 的影響有關係
he just said
他就說
In one of his articles he talked about
他有一篇文章就談到說
Europeanization of Chinese language and grammar or new ideas
中國的語言的歐化跟文法或新思想
What kind of connection should we have with each other?
到底彼此應該有怎麼樣的聯繫來想像
Finally, there is a very simple conclusion that
最後有一個很簡單的結論說
The biggest difference between Chinese and Western poetry
中西詩語最大的差別
not in grammar at all
根本不在文法
Thinking and Feeling Patterns
而是在思想與感覺樣式
He said the new sensory style of Chinese poetry
他說漢語詩的新感覺樣式
must be fresh
必須要有新鮮活潑的
metaphor hint contrast
隱喻 暗示 對比
This is the key to the development of Chinese
這才是漢語發展的關鍵
He does not deny that grammar is necessary
他並沒有否定文法是必要的
but he thinks
可是他認為
There must be metaphors, hints, contrasts
必須要有隱喻 暗示 對比
this concise
這種簡潔的
even a bit economical syntax
甚至有一點經濟的語法
to write poetry
來寫詩
Then such a new poem
那麼這樣的新詩
Only then can it lead to more rich meanings
才可以引發更多豐富的涵義
should we
那我們是不是應該
Everyone knows that Zhu Zhiqing's prose is very famous
大家都知道朱志清的散文很有名
Then let's take a look at a poem by Zhu Zhiqing
那我們來看看朱志清的一首詩
okay
好嗎
this very long poem
這首很長的詩
I only cited one of them
我只舉了其中一段
He said like evil beasts
他說就像惡了的野獸們
Instinctively feel like some blood and flesh
本能地想覺著些鮮血和肉一般
They also seem to be driven by something
他們也被什麼驅迫著似的
Think of these dull copper plates
想覺著這些暗淡的銅板
Bai Liang's role
白亮的角色
In their eyes, the warehouse is crowded and piled up
他們眼裡倉理擁擠著堆積著的
It's these homologs and toes
正是這些同源和腳趾罷了
It's just a doll
只是的人形罷了
from everything in kokura
從小倉的一切裡
I got to know each other quietly like this
這樣這樣悄然認識了
That self-authored Xi Si is modern
那自著習四的現代了
this is very clear
這個很清楚
he talks about capitalism
他講的是資本主義
There are three sources of economic modernity
在經濟現代性裡面有三大來源
The first source is capitalism
第一個來源就是資本主義
So if a man becomes a beast
所以人如果變成野獸
just a decorative figure
只是裝飾的人形
is this the modern we want
這是我們要的現代嗎
In Zhu Zhiqing's "Modern Times in Xiaocang"
在朱志清的這首小倉中的現代裡面
he shouted like this
他這樣子吶喊
or question like this
或者是這樣質疑
Another poem is also modern
另外一首詩也是現代派的
Chi Zhijun's very famous peach-colored cloud
吃植純非常有名的桃色的雲
He said that in the details of Shenxia
他說在細目的參俠裡
from chimney spirit
從煙囪靈中身上來的
big peachy cloud
大朵的桃色的雲
Made of a beautiful smokeberry
朵美麗煙莓做的
transparent peachy cloud
透明的桃色的雲
the last paragraph he said
最後一段他說
Girls who really create stressful problems
確造壓題的女生
The girl from the nose
女之宮從鼻子的這個仔
when the iron gate poured out
鐵門中湧出來的時候
beautiful peachy clouds
美麗的桃色的雲
become in the summer valley
就變做在夏季的山谷中
brewing madness rainstorm
釀造狂氣的 暴雨的
heavy and terrible dark clouds
沉重而可怕的烏雲了
you know the original one
你知道原來那個
Peach-colored clouds made of smoke mold
煙霉做的桃色的雲
about industrial development
講的是工業發展
But why does industrial development
可是工業發展為什麼
Feminines from that
整女工們從那個
After coming out of the narrow iron gate
狹窄的鐵門中出來以後
will become a rainstorm
會變成暴雨的
What about the heavy, terrible dark clouds?
沉重的 可怕的烏雲呢
you know here is talking
你知道在這裡是講
possible industrial development
工業發展可能帶來的
significant impact on people
對人的重大的影響
so it's economical
所以這也是經濟
Now a very important source in my heart
現在心裡面很重要的一個來源
industrial development
就是工業發展
third Feimin
第三個費民
That was the famous
也就是當時很有名的
Another Poet Feng Wenbing's Street
詩人馮文秉的另一首街頭
he himself said
他自己說
He later wrote this
他後來有一篇這個
flash text said
閃文就說
I myself walked to Wangfujing Street
我自己是走到王府井大街的時候
Standing on the street and seeing these scenes
站在街頭就看到這些景象
He said that there is no car pool on the street
他說行到街頭哪有汽車池過
no oil barrel is lonely
哪有油桶寂寞
oil drum P.O.
油桶 P.O.
come to pray
來 祈禱
Throw away the car's code X
丟起汽车的套码 X
How can Arabic numerals be lonely?
哪有阿拉伯数字寂寞
car lonely
汽车寂寞
lonely street
大街寂寞
human loneliness
人类寂寞
this song is very simple
这首是很简单
corpses are called streets
尸体就叫街头
He said I just stood on the street and saw
他说我只是站在街头就看到
But you will find that he is lonely again and again
可是你会发现他反复出现了寂寞
It is no longer in Chinese
再也不是国汉语里面的
lonely sandbar cold
寂寞沙洲冷
Or the loneliness is as deep as the loneliness of autumn
或寂寞无同深越所清秋那个寂寞
The loneliness that I understand is not
那个物我感通的寂寞不是
On the contrary, there is a distance between things and me
这反而是物我之间有距离的
The more objective I am, the more subjective I am
越客观我就越主观
The more I get separated from you, the new loneliness
我就跟你越疏离的新的寂寞
And what is this loneliness talking about
而这个寂寞讲的是什么
is city life
是城市生活
This is also an important source of economic modernity
这也是经济现代性很重要的一个来源
So let's take a simple example with three hands
所以我们透过三手简单的来举例
Discover how Chinese is modern
发现汉语如何现代
In fact, Chinese poets are pioneers
其实是汉语诗人做先锋
He does a lot of work that looks like alchemy
他做了好多看起来像练金术打造的工作
Through these poems we
我们透过这些诗语
Chinese poets can be seen
可以看到汉语诗人
how
是如何
Facing the modern times, attempting to enter the modern times
面對現代 企圖進入現代
And how to brew a new modernity while wandering
而在徘徊中又如何釀造新的現代
Finally I want to ask the question at the beginning
最後我想一開始提出的問題
maybe we don't have the answer
也許我們沒有解答
But through these arguments
但是透過這些論述
Maybe we can have a preliminary solution
也許我們可以有初步的一種解答
After the whole discussion, you will find that
整個討論下來你會發現是
The Pull Moment Between Precision and Multi-Benefit
精確與多益性之間的拉矩
Perhaps the first of these we can say
在這當中也許第一點我們可以說
Language is not just a tool
語言不只是工具
It is an organ that shapes the inner mind
它是一種形塑內在思想的器官
So you see so many commentators
所以你看前面那麼多論述者
how they use language to establish themselves
他們怎麼樣用語言來建立自己
Understand what others drive their ideas
理解他人推動他們的理念
Language is definitely not just on the truck
語言絕對不只是在貨運的卡車而已
the second
第二個
We need the language of logical cognition
我們需要邏輯認知的語言
It is also necessary to seek a language for cross-domain co-editing
也需要尋求跨域共改的語言
Cross-domain co-reform We have been talking about cross-domain
跨域共改 我們現在一直在講跨領域
cross field
跨領域
in the interdisciplinary process
在跨領域的過程裡面
how do we express
我們怎麼表達
How do we properly understand others
我們怎麼適度地理解他人
and the ability to incorporate new sympathies
以及能夠融會出新的共感
I think language also needs empathy
我想語言也需要共感
not just cognition
而不只是認知
third point
第三點
From this discourse
從這個論述裡面
We can see that language is constantly in transition
我們可以看到語言是不斷地在轉型中
and different cultures
而且是不同文化
From the process of handover and reflection
多從交接與反省的過程
It is ancient and modern, China and the West borrow from each other
是古今是中西彼此借取
Mutual construction and handover of cross-border civilizational achievements
互相建設交接跨界的文明成果
So what we call Chinese now
所以我們現在所謂的漢語
not only belong to a certain era
不單屬於某一個時代
a political entity
某一個政治實體
only a certain generation
某一個世代而已
It actually keeps us in the process of transformation
它其實是讓我們不斷地在轉型中
This is the real development of language
這才是真正的語言的發展
The development of Chinese language will not only be in China
漢語的發展不會只在中國境內
If you notice that Japan, South Korea, and Vietnam
大家如果注意到日本韓國越南
should be an important one
都應該是很重要的一個
We can even say that it is another
甚至我們可以說是另外一種
The scope of the study of modernity
現代性的研究的範圍
part in japanese
在日語的部分
like professor kim munjin
像金文津教授
He put his own Japanese
他把他自己的一本日文
translate into chinese
自己翻譯成中文
It is about the relationship between Chinese and the East Asian world
是講漢文跟東亞世界的關係
Speaking of Japan and South Korea
就談到日 韓
how to use your own way
是怎麼樣用自己的方式
to interpret classical Chinese
來解讀文言文
For example, reverse word order
比方說翻轉語序
add some special symbols
加一些特殊的符號
So he doesn't just have one transformation
所以他不是只有一種轉型
There is not only one way to face modern times
不是只有一種面對現代的方法
I think what I offer today is
我想我今天提供的是
China
中國境內
How to build through the mutual construction of China and the West
怎麼樣透過中西的相互建設
to achieve
來達成
not to say that achieved
也不是說達成
To continue to promote the transformation of Chinese
來持續推動漢語轉型
report here today
今天報告到這裡
thank you all
謝謝大家